one and okay. Here is lecture 16. And
if you remember, I ended up
the last lecture with this formula for
what I called a projection matrix.
And
maybe I could just recap for a minute.
What is that What is that magic formula
doing?
For example,
it's supposed to be it's supposed to
produce a projection. If I multiply by a
B, so I take P times B,
I'm supposed to project that
vector B
to the nearest point in the column
space.
Okay. Can I just
One way to recap is to take the two
uh extreme cases.
Suppose the vector B is in the column
space.
Then what do I get when I apply the
projection P?
So I'm projecting into the column space,
but I'm starting with a vector
in this case that's already in the
column space. So of course, when I
project it, I get
B again, right.
And we want to I want to show you how
that comes out of this formula. Let me
do the other the other extreme.
Suppose that vector is perpendicular to
the column space. So imagine this column
space as a plane, and imagine B is
sticking straight up perpendicular to
it.
What's the nearest point in the column
space
to B
in that case?
So what's the projection
onto the plane, the nearest point in the
plane, if the vector B that I'm looking
at is
got no component in the column space.
It's sticking completely 90° with it.
Then PB should be
zero, right.
So those are the two extreme cases.
The average vector has a component P in
the column space and a component
perpendicular to it. And what the
projection does is it kills this part
and it
preserves this part. Okay. Can we just
see why that's true? Just just
that formula
uh ought to work.
Let me start with this one.
What what vectors are in the are are
perpendicular to the column space?
Uh how do I see that I really get zero?
I have to think, what does it mean for a
vector B to be perpendicular to the
column space?
So if it's perpendicular to all the
columns,
then it's in some other space. We've got
our four spaces. So
the reason I do this is it's perfectly
using what we know about our four
spaces.
What's What vectors are perpendicular to
the column space?
Those are the guys in the null space of
A transpose, right?
That's the first section of this
chapter. That's the key geometry of
these spaces. If I'm perpendicular to
the column space, I'm in the null space
of A transpose. Okay. So if I'm in the
null space of A transpose, and I
multiply
this
big formula times B,
so now I'm getting PB. This is now the
projection
PB.
Do you see that I get zero? Of course I
get zero.
Right at the end there, A transpose B
will give me zero right away. So that's
why that zero is here.
Cuz if I'm perpendicular to the column
space, then I'm in the null space of A
transpose, and A transpose B is
zilch.
Okay. What about the other possibility?
What What How do I see that this formula
gives me the right answer if B is in the
column space?
So what's a typical vector in the column
space?
It's a combination of the columns.
How do I write a combination of the
columns? So So tell me, how would I
write
you know, your everyday vector that's in
the column space?
It would have the form A times some X,
right?
That's what's in the column space, A
times something.
That makes it a combination of the
columns. So these B's were in the in the
null space of A transpose, these guys in
the column space, those B's are AX's.
Right? If B is in the column space, then
it has the form AX.
I'm going to stick that on the quiz or
the final for sure. That you have to
real- realize, cuz we've said it like a
thousand times, that the things in the
column space are vectors A times X.
Okay. And do you see what happens now if
we use our formula? There's an A
transpose A gets canceled by its
inverse. We're left with an A times X.
So the result was AX, which was B.
Do you see that it works? This is that
whole business.
Cancel, cancel, leaving AX.
And AX was B. So that turned out to be B
in this
in this case.
Okay. So geometrically, what we're
seeing
is
we're taking a vector we we've got the
we've got the
column space.
And perpendicular to that is the
null space of A transpose.
And our typical vector B is out here.
There's zero, so there's our typical
vector B. And what we're doing is we're
projecting it
to P.
And the And of course, at the same time,
we're finding the other part of it,
which is E.
So the diff- the the two pieces, the
projection piece and the error piece,
add up to the original B.
Okay. That's That's like what our matrix
does.
So this is P P is This P is AB is Sorry,
is PB. It's the projection
applied to B.
And this one is Okay, that's a
projection, too.
That's a projection down onto that
space.
What's a good formula for it? Suppose I
ask you for the projection of the of the
projection matrix onto the
this space, this perpendicular space.
So if this projection was P,
what's the projection that gives me E?
It's
uh what I want is to get the rest of the
vector, so it'll be just I minus P.
times B. That's a projection, too.
That's the projection
onto the
perpendicular space.
Okay.
So if P is a projection, I minus P is a
projection. If P is symmetric, I minus P
is symmetric. If P squared equals P,
then I minus P squared equals I minus P.
It's just
the algebra is is only doing what your
your uh
uh picture is is completely telling you.
It's But the algebra leads to this
uh expression.
That expression for P
given
uh a basis for the subspace. Given the
matrix A whose columns are a basis for
our column space.
Okay. That's recap, cuz you you need to
see that formula more than once.
And now can I pick up on using it?
So now
and I and the
It's It's like uh
Let me do that again. I'll do
go go right through a problem that I
started at the end, which is
find a best straight line.
You remember that problem? I I picked a
particular uh set of points.
They weren't specially brilliant. T
equal 1 2 3.
The heights were 1
2 and then 2 again. So they were heights
were that point
that point, which makes it look like
I've got a nice 45° line, but then the
third point didn't lie on the line.
And I wanted to find the best straight
line.
So I'm looking for the the this line
Y equals C plus DT.
And
it's not going to go through all three
points, cuz no line goes through all
three points.
So I'm going to pick the best line.
The the best being the one that makes
the the overall error as small as I can
make it.
Now I have to tell you, what is that
overall error?
And
uh
Cuz that
that determines what's the winning line.
If we don't know I mean we have to
decide what we mean by the error.
What and then we minimize and we find
the right the best C and D. Okay.
So,
if again if if I went through this if I
went through that point, I would solve
the equation C plus D equals one.
Because at T equal to one, I'd have C
plus D and it would come out right. If
if if it went through this point, I'd
have C plus 2D equal to two.
Because at T equal to two, I would like
to get the answer two. At the third
point, I have C plus 3D because T is
three, but the the answer I'm shooting
for is two again.
So, those are my three equations.
And they don't have a solution.
But they've got a best solution.
What do I mean by best solution? So, let
me take time out to remember
what I'm talking about for best
solution.
So, this is my equation
B.
A is this matrix
1 1 1
1 2 3.
X is my only have two unknowns C and D.
And B is my right hand side 1 2 3.
Okay.
No solution.
Three I have a 3 by 2 matrix. I do have
two independent columns. So, I do have a
basis for the column space. Those two
columns are independent. They're a basis
for the column space, but
the column space doesn't include that
vector.
So,
best possible
in this
What would best possible mean?
The the way that comes out to linear
equations is I I want to minimize
the sum of these.
I'm going to make an error here. I'm
going to make an error here. I'm going
to make an error there.
And I'm going to
sum and square and add up those errors.
I So, it's a sum of squares. It's a
least squares solution I'm looking for.
So, if I those errors are the difference
between AX
and B.
That's what I want to make small.
And the way I'm measuring this, this is
a vector, right? This is E1 E2 E3. AX
minus B, this is the this is the E
the error vector.
And small means its length.
The length of that vector. That's what
I'm going to try to minimize. And it's
convenient to square.
If I make something small, I make
This is a This is a non This is a never
negative quantity, right? The length of
that vector.
The length will be zero
exactly when the when I have the zero
vector here. That's exactly the case
when
I can solve exactly. B is in the column
space. All great. But I'm not in that
case now. I'm going to have an error
vector E. What's this error vector in my
picture?
I guess what I'm trying to say is
there's there's two pictures of what's
going on.
There's two pictures of what's going on.
One picture is
in this
in this is the three points and the
line.
And in that picture,
what are the three errors? The three
errors are what I missed by in this
equation. So, it's this
this little bit here. That vertical
distance up to the line. There's one
Sorry, there's one and there's C plus D
and it's that difference.
Here's two and here's C plus 2D. So,
vertically, it's that distance. That's
that's That that little error there is
E1.
This little error here is E2.
This little error coming up is E3.
E3.
And what's my to- overall error is
E1 squared plus E2 squared plus
plus E3 squared.
That's what I'm trying to make small.
I
Some statisticians This is a big part of
statistics.
Fitting straight lines is a big part of
science and specifically statistics
where the right word to use would be
regression.
I'm doing regression here.
Linear regression.
And I'm
and I'm using this sum of squares as the
measure of error. Again, some
statisticians
would
be They would say, "Okay, I'll solve
that problem because it's the clean
problem. It leads to a beautiful linear
system."
But they would be a little careful about
least squares for
in this case.
If one of these points was way off.
Suppose I had a measurement at T equal
zero that was way off.
Well, would the straight line with the
best line be the same if I had this
fourth point? Suppose I have this fourth
data point.
No, certainly the line would
it wouldn't be that That wouldn't be the
best line.
Because that line would have a giant
error and when I squared it, it would be
like way out of sight compared to the
others.
So, the
this This would be called by
statisticians an outlier.
And they would not be happy to see the
whole problem turned topsy-turvy by this
one outlier, which could be a mistake
after all.
So, they wouldn't So, they wouldn't like
maybe squaring. If there were outliers,
they would want to identify them. Okay.
I'm not going to
I'm I'm taking the the but the but I I
don't want to
suggest that least squares isn't used.
It's the most used, but it's not
exclusively used because it's a little
overcompensates for outliers.
But because of that squaring. Okay. So,
suppose we don't have this guy.
We just have these three equations.
And
I want to make minimize this error.
Okay.
Now, what I said is
there's two pictures to look at.
One picture is this is this one. The
three points, the best line.
And the errors.
Now,
on this picture, what are these points
on the line? The points that are really
on the line.
So, they're
they're points. Let me call them P1, P2,
and P3. Those are three numbers.
So, this this height is P1.
This height is P2.
This height is
P3.
And what are those guys?
Suppose those were the three values
instead of
There's B1. Everybody's seeing all these
Sorry, the
my art is as usual not the greatest, but
there's the given B1,
the given B2,
and the given B3.
I promise not to put a single letter
more on that picture. Okay. There's
There's B1.
P1 is the one on the line and E1 is the
distance between.
And same at points two and same at
points three.
Okay.
So, what's up? What's up with those P's?
P1, P2, P3, what are they?
They're the components. They lie on the
line, right?
They're the They're the points which if
I if if instead of 1 2 2, which were
the B's.
Suppose I put
P1, P2, P3 in here. I'll figure out in a
minute what those numbers are. But I
just want to get the picture of what I'm
doing.
If I put P1, P2, P3 in those three
equations, what would be good about the
the three equations?
I could solve them.
A A line goes through the P's.
So, the P1, P2, P3 vector, that's in the
column space.
That is a combination of these columns.
It's the closest combination. It's this
picture.
See, I've got the two pictures. Like
here's the picture uh that shows the
points.
This is a a picture in a in a blackboard
plane.
Here's a picture
that's showing the vectors.
The vector B, which is in this case in
this example is the vector 1 2 2.
The column space
is in this case spanned by the
Well, you see A there. The column space
of the matrix 1 1 1 1 2 3.
And
this
picture shows the nearest point. There's
the that point P1 P2 P3, which I'm going
to
compute before the end of this hour,
is the closest point
in the column space. Okay.
Let me Let me not
I don't dare leave it any longer. Like
can I just compute it now?
So, I want to compute
find P.
All right, find P.
Find X, which is CD.
Find P and P.
Okay, and I really should put these
little hats on to to remind myself that
they're the
estimated.
The best The best line, not the perfect
line.
Okay.
Okay, how do I proceed? Let's just run
through the mechanics.
What's the equation for
X?
The equa- X hat.
The equation for that is A transpose A
X hat equals A transpose X.
A A transpose
B.
The most I I I
will venture to call that the most
important equation in statistics.
And in estimation.
And whatever you're Wherever you've got
error and noise, this is the estimate
that you use first.
Okay.
Whenever you're fitting things
by a few parameters, that's the equation
to use. Okay, let's solve it.
Uh what is A transpose A? So, I have to
figure out what these matrices are.
and
111123.
That gives me some matrix.
That gives me a matrix. What do I get
out of that? Three
uh six
six and
four and nine 14.
Okay.
And what do I expect to see in that
matrix that I do see it just before I
keep going with the calculation?
I expect that matrix to be symmetric.
I expect it to be invertible.
And near the end of the course, I'm
going to say I expect it to be positive
definite, but that's uh I that's a
future
fact about this crucial matrix A
transpose A. Okay, and now let me figure
A transpose B.
So, let me Can I tack on
B as an extra column here?
and tack on
the extra A transpose B is looks like
five and one and four and six 11.
So, I think my equations are 3C + 6D = 5
and 6D
plus four uh
6C plus 14D is 11.
Can I just for safety see if I did that
right? 111 * 122 is five.
123, that's one four and six 11. Looks
good.
These are my equations.
That's my my They're called the normal
equations.
I'll just write that word down because
it
So, I solve them.
I solve that for C and D.
I I would like to Before I solve them,
could I do one thing that's on the
that's just about here?
I would like to I'd like to find these
equations from calculus.
I'd like to find them
from this minimizing thing.
So, what's the first error? The first
error is what I missed by in the first
equation.
C plus D minus one squared.
And the second error is what I missed in
the second equation. C plus 2D minus two
squared. And the third error squared is
C plus 3D minus two
squared.
That's my overall squared error that I'm
trying to minimize.
Okay.
So,
How do How would you minimize that?
Okay, linear algebra has has given us
the equations for the minimum.
But
we could use calculus, too.
That's That's a function of two
variables, C and D.
And we're looking for the minimum.
So, how do we find it?
Directly from calculus,
we take partial derivatives, right?
We've got two variables, C and D.
So, take the partial derivative with
respect to C and set it to zero, and
you'll get that equation.
Take the partial derivative with respect
I'm
I'm not going to write it all out, just
you will.
The partial derivative with respect to
D,
it You know, it's going to be linear.
That's the beauty of least squares, is
that if if I have the square of
something
and I take its derivative, I get
something linear. And this is what I
get. So, this is the derivative of the
error with respect to C being zero, and
this is the derivative of the error with
respect to D being zero.
Wherever you look, these equations keep
coming. So, now I guess I'm going to
solve it. What will I do? I'll subtract
I'll do elimination, of course, cuz
that's only thing I know how to do. Two
of these away from this
would give me
Let's see, six. So, would that be two Ds
equals one?
Huh.
So, I wasn't I I was afraid these
numbers were going to come out awful.
But if I take two equa- two of those
away from that, the equation I get left
is 2D equals one. So, I think D is a
half.
And C is
whatever back substitution gives. 6D is
three. So, 3C plus three is five. I'm
doing back substitution now, right?
Three Can I do it in light letters? 3C
plus that 6D is three equals five. So,
3C is two. So, I think C is 2/3.
1/2 and 2/3.
So, the best line
the best line is the best line
is
the constant 2/3 plus 1/2
T.
And am I Is my picture more or less
right?
Let me write Let me copy that best line
down again. 2/3 and 1/2.
Let me
I'll put in the 2/3 and the half.
Okay.
So, what's this P1?
That's the value at T equal to one. At T
equal to one, I have 2/3 plus 1/2, which
is
What's that? 4/6 and 3/6. So, P1 Oh, I
promised not to write another thing on
this.
I'll Look, I'll I I'll erase P1 and I'll
put 7/6. Okay. And
Yeah, it's above one. And E1 is 1/6.
Right. You see it all, right? What's P2?
Okay, at the point T equal to two,
where's my line here? At T equal to two,
it's 2/3 plus
one, right? That's 5/3.
2/3 and T is two, so that's 2/3 and one
make 5/3. And that's sure enough, that's
smaller than the exact two.
And then the final P3, when T is three
Oh, what's 2/3 plus 3/2?
It's the same as 3/2 plus 2/3.
It's um
So, maybe 4/6 and 9/6, maybe 13/6. Okay.
And again, look. Oh, look at this. Okay.
You have to admire the beauty of this
answer.
Uh this what's this first error? So,
here are the errors, E1, E2, and E3.
Okay, what was that first error, E1?
Well,
if if we decide the errors counting up,
then it's 1/6.
And the last error, 13/6 minus the
correct two is 1/6 again.
And what's this error in the middle?
Let's see, The correct answer was two
two.
And we got 5/3 and it's the other
direction minus 1/3 minus 2/6.
That's our error vector.
In our picture, in our other picture,
here it is.
We just found P
and E.
E is this vector 1/6 minus 2/6 1/6.
And P is this guy. Well, maybe I have
the signs of E wrong. I think I have.
Let me Let me fix them.
Because I would like
this
1/6 I would like this plus the P to give
the original B. I want
P plus E to match B.
So I want minus a sixth
plus 7/6 to give the correct
B equal 1.
Okay.
Now
Okay, my my I'm going to take a deep
breath here
and ask
what do we know about this error vector
E?
You have seen now this whole problem
worked completely
through and I even think the numbers are
right.
So this P
So let me I'll write I'll write out what
if I can
put it down here. B is P plus E.
B I believe was 1 2 2.
The nearest point had 7/6
Um what were the others? 5/3
and 13/6.
And the E vector was minus a sixth
2/6 1/3 in other words and minus a
sixth.
Okay.
Tell just like tell me some stuff about
these two vectors. Tell me something
about those two vectors. Well, they had
to be right. Great. Okay. What else?
What else about those two vectors? The P
the the projection vector P and the
error vector E.
What else do you know about them?
They're perpendicular. Right.
Do we dare verify that?
Can we take the dot product of those
vectors?
I'm like getting like minus 7 over 36.
Can I change that to 10/6?
Oh God, come out right here.
Uh minus 7 over 36
plus 20 over 36 minus 13 over 36.
Thank you God. Okay.
And what else should we know about that
vector?
Actually, we know
I I I got to say we know even a little
more. This vector
E is perpendicular to P.
But it's perpendicular to other stuff,
too.
It's perpendicular not just to this guy
in the column space. This is in the
column space for sure.
This is perpendicular to the column
space. So like give me another vector
it's perpendicular to.
Another cuz it's perpendicular to the
whole column space, not just to this
this particular projection that that is
in the column space.
But it's it's perpendicular to other
stuff. Whatever is in the column space.
So tell me another vector in the col- Oh
well, I've written down the matrix.
So tell me another vector in the column
space.
Pick a nice one.
1 1 1.
It's what everybody's thinking.
Okay. 1 1 1 is in the column space and
this guy is supposed to be perpendicular
to 1 1 1. Is it?
Sure. If I take the dot product with 1 1
1, I get minus a sixth plus 2/6 minus a
sixth.
Zero.
And it's perpendicular to 1 2 3. Cuz if
I take the dot product with 1 2 3, I get
minus 1
plus 4
minus 3 zero again.
Okay. Do you see the
I hope you see the two uh pictures. The
picture here for vectors
and the picture here for the best line
and it's the same picture.
Just like it's in This one's in the
plane and it's showing the line.
This one never did show the line. This
In this picture, C and D never showed
up.
In this picture, C and D were
you know, they determined that line.
But the two are exactly the same. C and
D is the combination of the two columns
that gives P.
Okay.
So that's uh
least squares
and
the special but most important example
of fitting by straight line. So the
homework
that's coming then Wednesday ask you to
fit by straight lines.
So you're just going to end up solving
the key equation.
You're going to end up solving that key
equation and then P will be A X hat.
That's it.
Okay.
Now
can I put in a little
piece of linear algebra that I mentioned
earlier, mentioned again, but I never
did write.
And I've I should do it right.
It's the It's about this matrix A
transpose A.
There.
I was sure that that matrix would be
invertible.
And of course, I wanted to be sure it
was invertible because I planned to
solve the system with that with that
matrix.
So and I announced like
before the as the chapter was just
starting
I announced that it would be invertible.
But now I Can I come back to that?
Okay. So
So what I said was
that if
A has
independent
columns
then
A transpose A
is invertible.
And I would like to
first repeat that important fact
that that's the requirement that makes
everything go here.
It's the It's this independent columns
of A that that guarantees everything
goes through.
And think why.
Why does Why does this matrix A
transpose A Why is it invertible if the
columns of A are independent?
Okay. There's
I guess I'm I'm I'm wondering So So if
it wasn't invertible
So I want to prove that.
If If it isn't invertible, then what?
I want to reach
uh I want to follow that follow that
line of of thinking and see what I come
to.
Suppose So proof.
Suppose
A transpose A X is zero.
I'm trying to prove this. This is now to
prove.
I I don't like hammer away at too many
proofs in this course.
But this is like the central fact and it
brings in all the stuff we know. Okay.
So I'll start the proof.
Suppose A transpose A X is zero.
What what and I and I'm aiming to prove
A transpose A is invertible.
So what do I want to prove now?
So I'm I'm aiming to prove this fact.
I'll use this and I'm aiming to prove
that this matrix is invertible. Okay. So
if I suppose A transpose A X is zero,
then what conclusion do I want to reach?
I'd I'd like to know that
X must be zero.
I want to show X must be zero. To show
now, to prove X must
be the zero vector.
Is Is that right? That's what we worked
in the previous chapter to understand.
That a matrix was invertible
when
its null space is
only the zero vector.
So, that's what I want to show. How come
if A transpose AX is zero, how come
X must be zero?
What's going to be the reasoning?
Actually, I have two ways to do it.
Let me show you one way.
This is
So, here trick.
Take the dot product of both sides with
X.
So, I'll multiply both sides by X
transpose. X transpose A transpose AX
equals zero.
I shouldn't have written trick.
That makes it sound like just a dumb
idea. Brilliant idea, I should have put.
Okay.
I'll just put idea.
Now,
I got to that equation X transpose A
transpose AX equals zero and I'm hoping
you can see a
a
the right way to
to look at that equation.
It
What can I What can I conclude from that
equation? That if I have X transpose A
Well, what is X transpose A transpose
AX? Does that Do you see the Do you see
what it what it
what it's giving you?
I'm It's again going to be putting in
parentheses. I'm looking at AX, and what
am I seeing here?
It's transpose.
So, I'm seeing here this is
AX transpose
AX
equaling zero.
Now, if AX transpose AX, so like let's
call it Y or something. If Y transpose Y
is zero, what does that tell me?
That the vector has to be zero, right?
And this is the length squared. That's
the length of the vector AX squared.
That's AX times AX. So, I conclude that
AX has to be zero.
Well, I'm getting somewhere.
Uh now that I know AX is zero,
now I'm going to use my little
hypothesis. Somewhere
every mathematician has to use the
hypothesis.
Right?
Now, if A has independent columns
and we've we're at the point where AX is
zero,
what does that tell us?
I could I mean, that could be like a a
fill-in question on the final exam. If A
has independent columns and if AX equals
zero, then what?
Please say it.
X is zero. Right.
Which was just what we wanted to prove.
That Do you you see why that is?
If AX equals zero, now we're using
Here we used This was the square of
something. So, I I'll put in
little parentheses the the the
observation we made. That was a square,
which is zero, so the thing has to be
zero. Now we're using the
hypothesis of independent columns
that A has
independent columns.
If A has independent columns, this is
telling me X is in its null space,
and the only thing in the null space of
such a matrix is the zero vector.
Okay.
So, that's the the argument, and you see
how it really used our understanding of
the
of the uh sub of the null space.
Okay. That's that's great. All right.
So, where are we then?
That that board is like the backup
theory
that tells me
that this matrix had to be invertible
because these columns were independent.
Okay.
Uh there's one case
of independent There's one case where
the geometry gets even better.
When the When I
There's one case when columns are sure
to be independent.
And let me put that Let me write that
down, and that'll be the subject for
next time. Columns
are
sure are certainly independent,
definitely independent.
If
if they're perpendicular.
Oh, I've got to rule out the zero
column. Let me give them all length one,
so so they can't be zero. If
they are
if they are
perpendicular
unit vectors.
Like
the vectors
1 0 0
0 1 0
and 0 0 1.
Those vectors are unit vectors.
They're perpendicular,
and they certainly are independent.
And what's more, suppose they're
Oh, it's so nice. I mean, what is A
transpose A for that matrix? For the
matrix with these three columns, it's
the identity.
So,
here's the key to the to the lecture
that's coming.
If we're dealing with perpendicular unit
vectors,
and the word for that will be ortho See,
I could have said orthogonal, but I said
perpendicular. Ortho, and this unit
vectors
gets put in as the word normal.
Orthonormal vectors.
Those are the best columns you could ask
for.
Matrices with
whose columns are orthonormal. They're
perpendicular to each other,
and they're unit vectors.
Well, they don't have to be those three.
Let me do a final example over here.
Uh
How about one at an angle like that, and
one at 90 degrees?
That vector would be cos theta sin
theta.
A unit vector.
And this vector would be minus sin theta
cos theta.
That is our absolute favorite pair of
orthonormal vectors.
They're both unit vectors, and they're
perpendicular. That angle is 90 degrees.
So, like our job next time is
first to see why orthonormal vectors are
great, and then to make vectors
orthonormal by picking the right basis.
Okay. See you.
Thanks.